<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<JobDescription>
  <JobId id="JobId">2</JobId>
  <ClassTitle id="ClassTitle">Police Officer First Class</ClassTitle>
  <WorkingTitle id="WorkingTitle">Patrol Officer</WorkingTitle>
  <Grade id="Grade">L02</Grade>
  <Rank id="Rank">Police Officer First Class</Rank>
  <WorkingHours id="WorkingHours">Varied</WorkingHours>
  <Categories id="Categories">
    <Category id="Category">
      <Letter id="Letter">A</Letter>
      <Weight id="Weight">45</Weight>
      <Title id="Title">Patrol/Repression of Crime</Title>
      <PositionDescriptionFields id="PositionDescriptionFields">
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Patrols a geographic area during an assigned shift in a motorized vehicle and responds to radio calls from the public for routine or emergency situations, taking the appropriate action as needed.</PositionDescriptionItem>
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Uses knowledge of and skill in administering applicable procedures, rules, regulations and ordinances.</PositionDescriptionItem>
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Makes arrests and issues citations on violations as observed.  Uses knowledge of self defense; skill in the use of firearms; the ability to react in emergency situations; and the ability to interact effectively with persons of varied cultural, ethnic and religious backgrounds.</PositionDescriptionItem>
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Maintains security of closed commercial establishments, observing potential areas of illegal entry, checking and recording information regarding suspicious vehicles and persons. </PositionDescriptionItem>
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Demonstrates knowledge of Departmental report writing procedures.</PositionDescriptionItem>
      </PositionDescriptionFields>
      <PerformanceStandardFields id="PerformanceStandardFields">
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="A1">Aggressively patrols assigned area to initiate enforcement of observed violations and takes appropriate action to resolve conflict as appropriate.</PerformanceStandardItem>
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="A2">Takes appropriate steps in conducting arrest using knowledge of, and skill in resolving conflict and maintaining order in accordance with established Departmental Rules and Procedures, State and County Laws.</PerformanceStandardItem>
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="A3">Ensures security of closed commercial establishments by applying appropriate guidelines and procedures to particular assignments. Takes necessary steps to record information in a concise and factual manner.</PerformanceStandardItem>
      </PerformanceStandardFields>
    </Category>
    <Category id="Category">
      <Letter id="Letter">B</Letter>
      <Weight id="Weight">25</Weight>
      <Title id="Title">Preliminary Investigation/Reports</Title>
      <PositionDescriptionFields id="PositionDescriptionFields">
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Conducts preliminary investigations of law violations perpetrated within assigned area, including interviewing victims and witnesses.</PositionDescriptionItem>
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Preserves and protects area to be scrutinized and secures physical evidence and investigation in the prescribed manner.  Uses knowledge of and skill in applying applicable procedures, rules, regulations and ordinances to ensure effective preservation of crime scenes.</PositionDescriptionItem>
      </PositionDescriptionFields>
      <PerformanceStandardFields id="PerformanceStandardFields">
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="B1">Demonstrates tact in conducting investigations of law violations.  Handles victims and witnesses in a manner that is consistent with a high degree of proficiency and professionalism.</PerformanceStandardItem>
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="B2">Applies appropriate procedures in protecting areas to be scrutinized and collects all physical evidence.</PerformanceStandardItem>
      </PerformanceStandardFields>
    </Category>
    <Category id="Category">
      <Letter id="Letter">C</Letter>
      <Weight id="Weight">25</Weight>
      <Title id="Title">Arrests and Court Presentation</Title>
      <PositionDescriptionFields id="PositionDescriptionFields">
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Prepares and presents cases for judicial procedures and testifies in courts.  Uses knowledge of evidence collection and court proceedings.</PositionDescriptionItem>
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Exercises appropriate techniques in identification, apprehension and prosecution of those violating applicable laws and ordinances.</PositionDescriptionItem>
      </PositionDescriptionFields>
      <PerformanceStandardFields id="PerformanceStandardFields">
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="C1">Chronicles evidence and investigation in the prescribed manner on the appropriate form so as to be legible, accurate, factual, clear, concise, and acceptable in court of law.</PerformanceStandardItem>
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="C2">Demonstrates knowledge of and skill in following accepted techniques in the identification, apprehension, and prosecution of those violating applicable laws and/or ordinances.</PerformanceStandardItem>
      </PerformanceStandardFields>
    </Category>
    <Category id="Category">
      <Letter id="Letter">D</Letter>
      <Weight id="Weight">5</Weight>
      <Title id="Title">Other Assigned Duties</Title>
      <PositionDescriptionFields id="PositionDescriptionFields">
        <PositionDescriptionItem>Accepts other duties as assigned.</PositionDescriptionItem>
      </PositionDescriptionFields>
      <PerformanceStandardFields id="PerformanceStandardFields">
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="D1">Willingly accepts miscellaneous assignments as necessary or as assigned.</PerformanceStandardItem>
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="D2">Cooperatively performs tasks and duties which may not be specifically listed in the position description but are within the general operational category and responsibility level typically associated with the employee’s class of work.</PerformanceStandardItem>
        <PerformanceStandardItem initial="D3">Adjusts schedule as necessary.</PerformanceStandardItem>
      </PerformanceStandardFields>
    </Category>
  </Categories>
</JobDescription>